Edward Hellmich Papers
Edward Hellmich Papers
1953-2003
1953-1958
Hellmich, Edward J.
12 linear ft.
Photographs, company documents, memorabilia and artifacts relating to Edward J. Hellmich, co-founder of The Branchell Company and Hellmich Manufacturing Corp, which designed, manufactured, and sold melamine dinnerware
5483855
Biographical History
Edward J. Hellmich (1911?-2000?) was an American businessman. With his wife Mildred (Mimi), he founded and operated Hellmich Mfg. Co. and The Branchell Co., based in St. Louis, Missouri. Hellmich and Branchell, respectively, manufactured and sold melamine plastic dinnerware under the trade name Melmac. There was also a factory in Bayamon, Puerto Rico. The Hellmichs sold the company to Lenox, the well-known china company, in 1958. Kaye LaMoyne was one of the firm's primary designers, responsible for the Ebonyte and Color-Flyte lines.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Edward Hellmich Papers consists of artifacts, company histories, correspondence, legal papers, memorabilia, and photographs, most of which pertain to Hellmich Mfg. Co. and The Branchell Co., companies founded by Hellmich for the manufacture and sale of melamine plastic dinnerware.
Artifacts contains specimens of Melmac dinnerware (plates, cupes, bowls, serving platters, etc.) including examples of Branchell's Ebonyte and Color-Flyte lines. Many of the items have no company or brand markings whatsoever, suggesting they are prototype models. Also included here are specimens of flatware with melamine handles in various colors, as well as examples of small flower-shaped candle holders, as for use on birthday cakes.
Company histories contains histories of Hellmich Mfg. Co., The Branchell Co., and Melmac, written by members of the Hellmich family. There is also a published book on Melmac dinnerware.
Correspondence includes Hellmich Mfg. Co. individuals such as Kaye LaMoyne, Karl Gottschalk, and Ernest Hellmich, as well as with attorneys and Lenox, Inc. regarding the sale of the company to Lenox.
Legal papers includes articles of incorporation, contracts, notes, and similar items.
Memorabilia includes both company material, such as clippings, letterhead, and product tags; and personal material, such as an invitation to the Hellmichs' 50th wedding anniversary and a tribute to Mimi by Edward.
Photographs include a formal portrait of Edward Hellmich, staged photographs of Melmac dinnerware settings, and the Hellmich factory in Puerto Rico.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetically by title or topic.
Related Material
has a number of collections related to plastics. Please to locate other relevant collections and cataloged material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Hellmich, Edward J.; Hellmich, Ernest.; LaMoyne, Kaye.; The Branchell Co.; Hellmich Manufacturing Corp.; Zimmer, Gregory R., 1947 -- Melmac dinnerware.; Flatware -- Specimens.; Melamine.; Plastics -- History.; Plastics -- Marketing.; Plastics industry and trade.; Plastic tableware.; Plastic tableware -- Specimens.; Puerto Rico.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Contracts.; Legal documents.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Christina Hellmich, 2019.
Inventory
- Artifacts
  - Aztec line
    - Plate, large, dinner plate, "Aztec" line, cream-colored with red, yellow, and blue design; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Bowl, shallow bowl, "Aztec" line, dark cream, plain; 1 item (Box 1)
  - ColorFlyte line
    - Plates, medium, salad or dessert plates, ColorFlyte "Royale" line, in black (3) and pink (2); 5 items (Box 1)
    - Cup, tea or coffee cup, ColorFlyte "Royale" line, pinkish color; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Cream pitcher, ColorFlyte "Royale" line, pinkish color; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Bowl, medium, shallow bowl molded with handle, ColorFlyte (but not Royale), lime green; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Ebonyte line
    - Cake stand, forest green with design of Chinese[?] characters on top, two-piece construction joined with screw; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Bowl, medium, bright green bowl with two bamboo handles and design of Chinese[?] characters; "Ebonyte" on underside of base; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Lid, lid for bowl, above; 1 item (Box 2)
    - Cups, coffee or tea cups, reddish-orange color with single bamboo handle and design of Chinese[?] characters on outside; 7 items (Box 2)
    - Cups, coffee or tea cups, reddish-orange color with two bamboo handles and design of Chinese[?] characters on outside; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Creamers?, cup shape with pour spout, reddish-orange color with single bamboo handle and design of Chinese[?] characters on outside; 4 items (Box 2)
    - Lid, small, reddish-orange color, with design of Chinese[?] characters; 1 items (Box 2)
    - Platter, large, serving platter, forest green with design of Chinese[?] characters on top, "Ebonyte" and "K La Moyne" in gold on underside of base; 1 item (Oversize 2)
    - Platter, large, serving platter, lime green, no decoration or markings; possibly a prototype for the darker green one; 1 item (Oversize 2)
  - Unidentified product lines, several have some combination of "Branchell," "K. LaMoyne", "St. Louis, Mo", "Melmac", or "quality dinnerware" on the underside while others are entirely blank and are presumably prototypes
    - Bowls, small, black, no markings; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Lids, small, reddish-orange color, plain with no decoration; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Bowls, small, reddish color, no markings; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Saucers, reddish color, no markings; 4 items (Box 2)
    - Plates, large, dinner plates, red, no markings; 2 items (Box 3)
    - Bowl, large, red, no markings; 1 item (Box 3)
    - Flatware, metal with light grey handles, probably melamine; 2 items (Box 4)
    - Flatware, metal with dark grey handles, probably melamine; 5 items (Box 4)
    - Flatware, metal with dark pinkish handles, probably melamine; 5 items (Box 4)
    - Flatware, metal with turquoise handles, probably melamine; 2 items (Box 4)
    - Bowls, medium, medium size, no markings, one each of pale yellow, peach, tan, and cinnamon color; 4 items (Box 4)
    - Bowl, large, black with design of pink, blue, and yellow balloons[?] and streamers; underside of base reads "Carnival"; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Bowl, large, black with faded/rubbed design of pink, blue, and yellow flowers; underside of base reads "Pinks"; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Teacup, yellowish cup with handle, "Melmac"; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Tumbler, small, pinkish color, "Melmac"; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Tumbler, medium, white, "Melmac"; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Sugar bowls[?], small open-topped containers, one in pinkish and one in grey, "Melmac"; 2 items (Box 5)
    - Teacup, "Lenoxware," white with handle; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Platter, large, large cake or serving platter, black, no markings, with decorative metal ring on base; 1 item (Oversize 1)
    - Bowl, large, large serving or salad bowl, black, no markings, with decorative metal ring on base; 1 item (Box 6)
    - Bowl, large, large serving or salad bowl, black, no markings, with decorative metal swirls on edge; 1 item (Box 6)
    - Bowls, small, small soup or cereal bowls, black, no markings, with decorative metal swirls on edge serving as handle; 2 items (Box 6)
    - Lids, small lids which fit bowls, one with a simple metal knob and the other with decorative metal swirls matching the bowls; 2 items (Box 6)
    - Bowl, medium, black, no markings, no decoration; 1 item (Box 6)
    - Bowl, medium, black, no markings, decorative metal ring on base; 1 item (Box 6)
    - Metal decorations, decorative metal swirl pieces; 2 items (Box 6)
    - Plates, medium, salad or dessert plates, red, no markings, possibly prototype; 2 items (Box 7)
    - Salad server set, red, no markings; two separate pieces, both rounded but one is molded with a fork-shaped design; 2 items (Box 7)
    - Serving plate, grey, oval with two lobes; 1 item (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Candle holders, small plastic holders for birthday cake candles; includes one set mounted on printed cardstock, as originally sold; 25+ items (Box 5)
    - Dish, small, small white plastic dish, printed on underside with "#10 Hellmich Mfg Corp Bayamon, P.R. 5-29-55" and 9 small circles in a diamond shape; printed on the interior is a message that begins "Ed - would like you to have this…" and ends with "Ever, Dave"; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Eyeglasses, pair of eyeglasses in a cream-colored plastic, left arm says "Raybert" and "SHE"; may not be a Hellmich product; 1 item (Box 5)
- Company histories
  - Branchell Company history, 2003; undated; includes one copy with extensive annotations and corrections in unknown hand (Box 8)
  - "History of business" by Mildred Hellmich, Apr 1973; photocopy of handwritten document (Box 8)
  - "Melmac" by Edward Hellmich, undated; handwritten, 3 pp. (Box 8)
  - Melmac Dinnerware / Gregory R. Zimmer and Alvin Daigle, Jr., LW Book Sales, 1997; published book (Box 8)
- Correspondence
  - Gottschalk, Karl, 1955 (Box 8)
  - Hellmich, Ernie, 1955-1958; undated (Box 8)
  - LaMoyne, Kaye, 1953; 1955 (Box 8)
  - Lawyers, various, 1956-1958; relating to sale of Hellmich Mfg. to Lenox (Box 8)
  - Lenox, Inc., 1958 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1955; 2002,; undated (Box 8)
- Legal papers
  - Agreement to sell, 1958; several copies and supporting documentation (Box 8)
  - Articles of incorporation, Hellmich Mfg. / Caribe Hellmich Mfg., 1953 (Box 8)
  - Driver's license / Licensia de conductor, Puerto Rico, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Contracts to sell and manufacture, 1953; 1956 (Box 8)
  - Employment agreement, 1958 (Box 8)
  - Lease, Puerto Rico property, circa 1953 (Box 8)
  - Loans and notes, 1958-1959 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1958; 1963,; 1968 (Box 8)
  - 50th wedding anniversary invitation, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Guest book, Puerto Rico, 1953-1964 (Box 8)
  - Letterhead, product tags, etc., undated (Box 8)
  - Tribute to Mimi Hellmich by Edward Hellmich, undated (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Ebonyte dinnerware, three-piece set, black with decorative metal swirls; appears to be same line as items in Box 6; 1 item (Oversize 2)
  - Edward Hellmich, undated; formal portrait photo (Box 8)
  - Melmac place settings, undated; probably for advertising (Box 8)
  - Puerto Rico plant, circa 1953-1960 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, most are candid shots in and around the Puerto Rico factory (Box 8)